So to get started, I'm going to create
a simple little program using Python.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna create,
uh, the typical print and hello world.
So print and hello world, like, so, and I'm
just gonna put a little input at the end
so that it's,  gives me an opportunity to
press a key, to slow or stop the program.
Okay, so I'm going to run this in this
editor, this editor is IDLE, this is
something that you get with Python
when you install it on your computer.
So if I want to run it, I can just simply go up
to run, run module, I'm just gonna quickly save
it and you'll see that we have a hello world
and it's waiting for me to press a key so I'll
just do that and it closes the program off.
Now not only will it run there, but
it'll also run in command so let me
just open up a command window a moment.
Now off the route directory I have a
directory called Python, so I'm just gonna
go into there, and within here, if I just
do DRI, which gives me a directory listing,
I should be able to see the application.
So, if I key in the application, now I can do it
like this and what happens is it puts a speech
mark around it that's only because I used a
space, if I hadn't used a space, it would just
simply, uh, be a straightforward command to type
in, but as you can see, it's hello, world dot
P Y the P Y indicates that it's a Python file
and if I press return you'll see that hello
world is working perfectly fine, there you go
it's working just below and I'll press return.
Now I can actually read the contents of
that file, so I can just use the command
type press return and you can see that
it's still in high level language.
So what's happening is there is a Python
application running in the background when
it recognizes that I'm using a P Y file
it simply runs that application by passing
the instructions one at a time through the
interpreter and pops it out the other side.
I'm gonna show you what would happen
if I didn't have the Python installed.
So as you can see, this is a different version of
windows now this version of windows doesn't have
Python installed, but I have put the program on.
So it's gonna go into the folder a moment.
So CD Python and hopefully we should see you the
file and there it is and again, I'll do a type
and show you the contents of the file and you'll
see, it's exactly the same as it was before.
However, this time when I try to run
the application, we get an error.
Well, actually we don't get an error because in
windows 10, what it did was it recognized that
it was a py file and it also recognized that
there wasn't an application associated with
it  so um, I can go to more apps and there's
nothing there, had I had the software installed
on my computer I would be able to use it, as
you can see, none of this relates to Python I
can't use any of it so the program won't run.
So that's the important thing to understand
that whilst you don't have the interpreter
software installed on your computer, you're
not gonna be able to run the application.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm going to create
a, an application using C sharp in visual studio.
Okay.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm going to
demonstrate the same principles using  C sharp.
So first of all, I'm gonna create a
new project  and we're gonna use a
console app, we're gonna use this one.
We're gonna use the, uh, console
app, which is, um, windows only.
So let me just see if I can find that a moment.
So C sharp and console there you go.
So we're gonna create a standalone
using their .net framework.
Next.
Um, I'm gonna save it in a folder
called compiled and in this case,
I'm just gonna call it hello world.
Like so create, okay.
You can see we've got, uh, the
framework for this application.
So it's, uh, slightly more complex than we saw
with Python, but I'm just going to do a console
dot right line and it's gonna be hello world,
just like we had before and again, need to put
the semicolon at the end and just like before,
I'm just gonna create a simple pause for it.
So it's console read line and
that should be all she wrote.
Okay.
So if I start this application up, What will
happen is a window will pop up with hello
world on it and a flashing cursor and there
it is, hello world with a flashing cursor.
If I press return, it closes down the application
because that's basically what it's supposed to do.
Now you don't wanna see it there, you
wanna see it outside of visual studio.
What I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna close
the visual studio application, like, so.
Now the file is actually nestled in amongst of
other folders so I'm just gonna bring this up,
there it is compiled, hello world, hello world,
go into bin debug and there's my file there.
So if I double click on this, it should
run the application and there it is.
It's running perfectly fine if I press return,
it closes the window, okay that's one way of
showing you, but let's get the command line.
I'm gonna go to CD compiled
and have a look into directory.
We've got hello world so CD hello world and then
directory again and it's hello world again so
the hello world, quite a few of those going.
Which directory look, and we're gonna go into
bin inside there we're gonna go into Debug.
Oops.
Skip that again debug and
then I it's, uh, in here.
So there it is.
So if I type in hello, world .exe press
return, you'll see the hello world.
Now you see that it actually ran a lot
quicker than we did with the interpreter.
When I press return, it
takes us back to the prompt.
So that's showing you it running in an
environment that is, has been set up for it.
But what about like we did with Python, we run
it in an environment that it's not familiar with.
So let's show you what happens there.
Okay.
So we've got the C prompt going.
I'm gonna go to CD compiled.
Quick Dir, we're gonna go into, well,
actually we haven't gonna go anywhere.
I've just transferred the exe file across.
So if I just run, hello, world dot exe, now,
if you remember, when we ran the Python, it
didn't work, but as soon as I press the return,
there you go the hello world is working fine.
So that's how a compiled work version works now.
So hopefully that's given you some indication
of the differences between a compiler and an
interpreter, and certainly how the programs work.